JACK: Torchwood.
Outside the government, beyond the police.
Tracking down alien life on Earth
and arming the human race against the future.
The 2 1 st century is when everything changes.
And you've gotta be ready.
Hello, there.
Apologies for the unplanned touchdown,
just hit some rotten turbulence.
-Captain Jack Harkness.
-Diane Holmes, pilot.
Is this some sort of secret base?
You must show me around one day, Captain.
-Everything all right?
-How long before we head off again?
-My uncle's expecting me.
-When did you leave?
-About half an hour ago.
-Which date?
-Today, December the 18th.
-Which year?
Which year? Which year, I need to know.
195 3.
-There's no need to be frightened.
-Who are you exactly?
The least you know about us, the better.
Meet the team.
-Toshiko.
-Gwen.
Doctor Owen Harper.
-John Ellis.
-Emma Louise Cowell.
-Diane Holmes.
-Please, follow me.
-At least it wasn't a spaceship full of aliens.
-That might have been easier.
But how can you travel 50 years in half an hour?
Your aircraft slipped through
a transcendental portal.
-A what?
-JACK: A door in time and space.
It's some kind of trick, it has to be.
Tosh?
(CLEARS TH ROAT)
Celebrations of the Millennium
in your respective home cities.
Photographs documenting the development
of Cardiff Bay from the ' 50s to the present day.
Blueprints of modern day aeroplanes.
But if all this is true, then how do we get back?
You don't.
According to history, your plane never returned.
I'm sorry.
What's gonna happen to us?
Never mind about us.
What happened to everyone else?
Our families.
Your father died in 1959. He was 48.
Dad said he'd die young.
All the men in the munitions factory did.
Your mother lived till she was 81, though.
I know this is hard to take in,
but is there anyone else?
My son, Alan Ellis.
He was born on the 6th of April, 1937.
14 Park Place, Grangetown. He might still be alive.
The archives in the ' 50s
weren't that well-documented.
We'll try again tomorrow.
Right now, you need to get some sleep.
Friends? Uh, boyfriend?
Not really. Never stayed in one place long enough.
It's a bit basic.
Not when you've slept in barracks.
I was going to close a deal
on a shop in Dublin tomorrow.
-What do you trade in?
-Uh, food, knick-knacks, essentials.
-What are you after?
-A bit of music.
(STATIC ON RADIO)
(BEETHOVEN'S MOONLIGHTSONA TA
PLAYING ON RADIO)
(CLEARS TH ROAT)
There's, uh, photographs of my family in here.
I'll see what I can do.
Don't worry, Captain Harkness,
I'll look after the ladies.
Call me Jack.
(GIRLS LAUGHING)
-Who else is here?
-Couple of young girls. Pretty dress.
Thank you. I made it myself.
-Where are you from?
-Bristol.
What were you going to Dublin for?
Auntie Nora's ill
and Uncle Finn can't manage the children.
It'll be good practice
for when I have children of my own mum says.
(BELL TIN KLING)
She's gone next door so Uncle Finn can telephone.
She'll know I'm missing by now.
Emma, she found out in 195 3.
Over 50 years have passed, remember?
What will she think happened?
It must have been like one of those murders
where they never find the body.
They seemed to think
the plane went down in the sea.
These will be your means of identification
for the authorities.
We've set up bank accounts for you,
but for now we'll be giving you a daily allowance,
so that you can practise with the currency
and money management.
David Ward?
Sally-Anne Hope.
Deborah Morrison,
and it's spelt how Deborah Kerr spells it.
Your background stories should incorporate
the skills you already have.
For instance, John,
you could have run a corner shop.
No.
-We can fake references.
-You can't take away our names.
For God's sake, man, it's all we've got left.
It's my son's name, it's the name above my shop.
(SIGHS)
You're right, I didn't think.
You should keep your name.
IANTO: I'd suggest you use £2 5 for your food,
and £20 for luxuries like cigarette, magazines...
EMMA: My dad only made £10 a week.
Things are a lot more expensive now.
-How did it do that?
-It's automatic.
-It knows you're there.
-But how?
There are wave bouncing detectors
which emit high frequency radio waves,
-and then look for reflections...
-Bananas!
Of course, bananas are far more interesting.
Look at all this.
We'd just come off rationing in ' 5 3.
-Yeah, sorry, we are a consumer society.
-It's bloody fantastic.
-How much food money have I got left?
-£15.40.
-£12 . 10, you'll ruin your teeth.
-You sound like my mum.
They sell films in boxes
and you can watch them at home.
I love going to the pictures.
Good God.
Welcome to the wonderful world
of scantily dressed celebrities.
Super Excel Waterproof Luscious Lashes Mascara.
I've got to have that.
-There's children around.
-She's a children's TV presenter.
So you like the musicals?
My best friend Kate and I went to
see CalamityJane five times. I've got the LP.
You all right?
What does that mean?
I'm just gonna take a look at the stadium.
You girls stick together now.
I'll be back for supper.
Excuse me. Do you know a man called Alan Ellis?
He used to live here.
No, sorry, mate.
(SIGHS)
I'm going to check on the plane this afternoon.
Want to come?
I'm going to watch this.
And maybe make some paper chains.
I wonder what work I can get in aviation.
I'm going to have to find a husband.
(GIRLS CHATTERING)
-All right? I'm Alesha, this is Jade.
-H i.
-I'm Emma.
-Diane.
Excuse me, I have to get ready.
-Where did you get those shoes? They're lush.
-Thanks.
Hello, old girl. Did you miss me?
I've, uh, I've been reading up on you.
England to Australia in four days, 1952,
that is impressive.
-Yeah, terrible wind across the Bengal Bay.
-Something you ate?
Uh... So, how did you get into this?
Ferried planes during the war.
Of course, when it was over, we were supposed
to revert to being dutiful wives and daughters.
But I'd got a taste for it. No pig-headed man
was going to tell me what to do.
Ah.
Sky Gipsy?
After the engine.
The De Havilland Gipsy Six, a work of genius.
Tuned with a higher compression ratio so it can
squeeze far more energy from its air-fuel mixture.
-Can I take her up?
-No.
-You could get arrested. You haven't got a licence.
-But I...
(SIGHING) Bugger. It's no longer valid.
I guess I'm just another pig-headed man
telling you what to do.
Well, you'd better make it up to me.
I want to learn all about this new world.
Blackpool were 3-1 down,
then Stanley Matthews worked his magic.
He scored two goals in the last 20 minutes.
Bolton lost 4-3.
My boy was on his knees, punching the air.
The FA Cup Final live in my own living room.
I charged the lads a shilling each
to come and watch.
Ever the business man, eh, John?
-That's an American accent, isn't it?
-That's right.
So how did you end up here,
doing whatever it is that you do?
It's a long story.
I'm a slow drinker.
You know everything about me.
What's the problem?
It gets kinda complicated.
What, did you fall through time, too?
Yeah, you could say that.
Sorry, mate, you can't smoke in here.
What are you doing Christmas Eve?
We could go carol singing.
(LAUGHING HYSTERICALLY)
I'm sorry, love, but I'll be getting hammered.
-Where are your families?
-No idea.
We grew up in care.
Like a children's home?
-I haven't got anyone else, either.
-What happened to you?
My parents are dead,
so I came down here to start afresh.
So they didn't leave you a house or anything?
No.
I've got nothing.
Were you close to them?
Yes.
I loved them very much.
Must have been an awful Christmas for them,
thinking I'd drowned.
I just want to know what kind of life he had,
my son. He might have kids.
I could be passing my own flesh and blood
in the street. Find him, Jack.
He's all I've got left.
Cheers.
-What?
-I'm waiting for you to pull out my chair.
Let me get this straight.
You expect equality and chivalry?
I don't see why they should be mutually exclusive.
Well, if it makes you happy.
Your chair, ma'am.
Thank you.
So, what other strides have women made?
Well, on the strange but true, how about this?
You don't have to have sex to have kids any more.
What?
How come?
Get yourself inseminated with a sort of syringe,
cheery little process.
Seriously, men donate sperm anonymously.
A little shuffle into a pot at a sperm bank.
And they say romance is dead.
Oh, come on, I wasn't born yesterday.
No, but for a bird who's going on 90,
you look pretty hot.
-What was your favourite song?
-Well, it's hard to say.
I know what mine was.
What do you think you're playing at?
I thought I could trust you to behave.
-Where do you want to go now?
-Well, I'm in your hands.
(SIGHING) Well, we could go back to mine.
You could read up about yourself on the net.
That sounds like a line. Um, it's not a line.
I'm not chatting you up, not because
I don't think you're attractive, because you are,
but because I wouldn't want you
to think I was taking advantage of you.
Got any Scotch?
-I don't see why she had to get you involved.
-She called me. She was upset.
-She was drinking.
-I only had half a glass.
Enough to make a show of yourself.
We're not meant to draw attention to ourselves.
We're not the same as them.
We can't trust anyone.
-Will you be okay now, Emma?
-Don't worry, I won't let her out of my sight again.
I don't like liver.
Sit down, young lady,
and be grateful for what you're given.
-And why should I listen to you?
-Emma.
Only my dad gets to talk to me like that.
I'm never going to see him again, am I?
Or my mum, or my best friend,
or my dog, and I miss them !
And I hate this filthy stinking place.
(DOOR SLAMS)
I never had this sort of trouble with my son.
Women have been to space, too, you know.
You got a lot of catching up to do.
-Do you have a girlfriend?
-No.
So who do all those beauty products belong to?
-Uh, me, actually.
-No?
(TROUBLE BY RAY LAMONTAGN E
PLAYING ON STEREO)
Oi, real men can moisturise, too, you know.
It's not very homely here.
No, I'm not here that much.
It doesn't seem worth the effort.
-You smoke too much.
-So I gather.
Amelia Earhart. She disappeared in 1932 .
-Do you think she's still out there somewhere?
-No, I doubt it.
One in a zillion chance you ending up here.
A whole new world.
Oh, it's not so bad once you get used to it.
I reckon you'll fit in just fine.
I'm glad you haven't got a girlfriend.
Me, too.
Emma is my auntie's step-daughter.
She was meant to spend Christmas
in Cardiff with a friend,
but they had this awful argument last night
and, uh, she rang me. Got my number from mam.
The thing is, she doesn't really
want to go back home so I thought,
I thought maybe she could stay with us.
We've got a lot to catch up on.
For Christmas?
-I'd better get a bigger turkey.
-Oh !
-Thanks.
-Aw, this is Rhys, my long-suffering boyfriend.
And he lives here.
-Don't your parents mind?
-Emma's parents are a bit religious.
Oh, uh, better not tell them
you saw my morning glory then, eh?
The thing is, I couldn't tell him
your parents were dead.
He'd ask too many questions.
The thing is, he doesn't know exactly what I do.
(WHISPERING) Just...
We can't expect John and Diane to look after her.
I mean, they're complete strangers.
I had to take her in.
Diane didn't even come home last night.
Uh, I think she was in a BandB. I'm gonna
take her job-hunting later if that's all right.
Jack, John's son, I think I've found him.
Come and meet Alan, though I'm not sure
how much help he'll be to you.
Alan, there's someone here to see you.
He's a nephew on your father's side.
-He's been tracking down the family history.
-Is Sally coming?
Sally is his wife. She passed away a while back.
Sorry, this isn't one of his better days.
-What's wrong with him?
-Alzheimer's.
-What's that?
-He's senile.
He doesn't remember who he is most of the time.
Couldn't live at home any more.
He'd leave hobs on, forget to dress, you know.
He never had any children
so there was no one there to look after him.
That's you and your dad,
playing footy out the back.
That's your dad and your mum
and your new television set.
-When can I go home?
-N U RSE: You're not well enough, love.
I don't like it here. They took my clothes.
I'll have a word, they're probably in the wash.
Keeps me going, this one.
What did he do for a living? Was he in retail?
Oh, I think he was a fireman.
That's what I did. In the war.
-£60 for half an hour!
-Ah, no worries. I'll pay.
(GASPING) Cessna ! Oh, it's my first plane.
I bought one after the war.
They've hardly changed. Dream to fly.
We'll soon get you back behind the...throttle.
Thanks, Owen.
Matthews did three set-ups in 20 minutes
then Bill Perry cracked home the winner.
You said he had wings on his feet,
that's why he was called a winger.
-You used to say clever things like that.
-Blackpool won !
-Yes.
-Oh !
Alan, it's me, your dad.
I bought you that Football Annual
you wanted for Christmas, Alan.
It was in my desk drawer.
Alan, please?
N U RSE: Everything all right?
He remembered who won the FA Cup Final
when he was a boy.
He sometimes remembers snippets from
his childhood. It's quite common with dementia.
When's Dad coming, Mum?
N U RSE: I'm not your mum, love.
JOH N : Alan?
Who are you?
John's witnessing the end of his world,
the end of his line. And we can't help.
There's no puzzle to solve, no enemy to fight,
just three lost people
who've somehow become our responsibility.
Best I can do is Friday 29th, 3:00.
-Can't you take her up today?
-Fully booked.
Oh, it's all right. I've flown for years.
I can go up on my own.
Not without a licence, sorry.
Erm, maybe you could cancel someone?
We'll pay extra.
I couldn't do that to my regulars now, could I?
Look, it's fine. Book me in for the 29th.
It's Diane Holmes.
Diane, I'm really sorry. I should have called ahead.
For goodness sake. This is so silly.
Leave it.
I can't if I want to fly a jet plane,
'cause that's all flying is now,
sitting on your backside pressing buttons.
You used to have to know how to fix an engine,
how to gauge the wind but...
Leave it.
Open this.
Oh !
It's beautiful.
Well, how did it go?
This coat I'm wearing is their latest fashion,
' 50s inspired.
-They offered me a job on the spot.
-Oh, that's brilliant!
Now we need to find you a flat
somewhere near here.
The shop's in a new branch in London.
I've always dreamt
about working in a London fashion house.
They open the day after Boxing Day.
I'll be a shop girl and a trainee buyer,
and I can house-share.
-They've given me contact numbers.
-London's a big city.
-That's what my mum used to say.
-There's no rush.
There's nothing to keep me here.
I'm sure we can find you something in Cardiff.
You keep looking.
I need to make a plan, get work,
get my driving licence.
-It'll all help.
-Thanks, Jack.
(SIGHS)
Uh, I was looking for a bus timetable.
I wanna get out to the DIY store,
see if there's any work going.
-Best of luck.
-Thank you.
-Where are you taking me?
-We're here.
Bear with me.
Oh, we have had such a girly day shopping.
What's up?
Your mum rang.
Mmm-hmm.
Funny thing, she's no idea who Emma is.
No?
And I'm thinking back
to you and me on the couch,
work calls, you go out in the middle of the night
and come back with a surprise relative.
So, let's have it, who exactly is Pollyanna?
(LAUGHS N ERVOUSLY)
Aw, is it to do with work?
It's so hard to explain.
Do you even know her?
She was lost. I'm sorry.
What worries me is how easy it seems to be
for you to lie to me, Gwen.
It's my fault. I'll leave by tomorrow.
You don't have to go. She's 18 years old.
I couldn't turn my back on her.
(DOOR SLAMS)
It's like two separate worlds.
There's Torchwood and then there's real life.
That's why you've got to let me go.
I, uh, couldn't help noticing you standing out here
in that beautiful dress.
This beautiful dress is a gift from my lover.
Then he is a fool to let you go out in it alone.
What shall we drink to?
Chance meetings.
(TH E GOOD LIFEBY TONY BENNETT
PLAYING ON CAR STEREO)
-Hello?
-My car keys are missing.
John was behind the counter earlier on
and I can't get hold of him.
He's going home.
(BEEPING)
John?
(BEEPING CONTIN U ES)
John !
JOH N : Let me go!
(GASPS)
You can't just throw it away, not without trying.
I'm not as strong as you. You don't understand.
I do. I was born in the future. Lived in your past.
My time has gone, too.
Why are you doing this?
Speaking to me in bloody riddles,
keeping me here when my wife is dead,
my son is a shell...
John, you're still young.
-You can get work, make friends, start a family.
-I did all that, Jack.
Years ago. When I was meant to.
-I wish I could say something...
-There's nothing to say or do.
-I can't leave you here.
-Then we'll wait.
The sun will rise, we'll have some breakfast,
take a walk.
Yes.
A new day.
And I'll suffer it all and smile and wag my tail.
And then as soon as your back is turned,
I'll make sure I do it properly.
Because I want to die.
You don't get reunited, John. It just goes black.
-How do you know?
-I died once.
-Who are you?
-A man, like you,
out of his time,
alone and scared.
-How do you cope?
-It's just bearable.
It has to be.
-I don't have a choice.
-But I do.
If you want to help me,
let me go with some dignity.
Don't condemn me to live.
Are you scared?
Yes.
(SIGHING)
Emma, these are your tickets, okay?
On the back is your seat number,
keep this with you at all times.
I've also got you a return, just in case.
Now, don't go talking to any strangers
and phone me as soon as you get there, okay?
No!
I'm not letting you do this.
-I'm not a possession, Owen.
-You can't do this. It's madness.
If I listened to everyone who told me that,
I wouldn't have broken any records.
You don't have to go.
If I don't, then I'll always wonder what it's like.
London, Gwen !
Okay.
Go on.
Diane, you're not thinking straight,
we can talk about this.
No, I'm sorry, Owen.
We can make this work,
you belong here now, with me.
-I belong in the sky.
-Well, we can get you up in the sky.
In a couple of months,
you can fly whenever you want.
Look, weather conditions are the same
as the day we arrived.
-That rift will open again. I can feel it.
-Diane, listen to me, there is no way back.
-You cannot get home.
-Then it will take me somewhere new.
Merry Christmas!
-I'll come with you.
-I fly solo, Owen.
-I go faster and further than others.
-We have no idea how this rift works.
You could end up anywhere.
-That's the beauty of it.
-It's too dangerous!
-It's what I do.
-What about me?
Please. Please.
Don't go.
What memories I'm taking with me.
Merry Christmas!
Because when you take off together,
it's the next best thing to flying.
Somebody's not only kidnapping weevils,
they're causing them pain.
These guys are using weevils
to carry out the perfect murder.
You want to release a weevil
in the middle of Cardiff!
I've been having sex with someone else.
H is name's Owen.
Who are you, Owen Harper?
We're going to hunt you down,
and we're going to make you surrender
that creature that you kidnapped.
Out there in the darkness, something is coming.